<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A commemoration of the inestimable graces and benefites of God, infused through the bryght lyght of the knowledge of his holy word, in our most dradde soueraigne lorde Henry the eyght, by the grace of God kyng of Englande and of Fraunce, defender of the the fayth, lorde of Irelande, and in erth the supreme heed next and immediate vnder Christe of the Churche of Englande, with hartye prayse and thankes gyuyng vnto God for the same, / composed uppon the glad prophecy and ioyefull psalme of Benedictus dominus deus Israel. &amp;c..</title>
            <author>Pylbarough, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1540</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 54 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B08002</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20521</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S94811</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">68222602</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 68222602</idno>
            <idno type="VID">183786</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B08002)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 183786)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2198:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A commemoration of the inestimable graces and benefites of God, infused through the bryght lyght of the knowledge of his holy word, in our most dradde soueraigne lorde Henry the eyght, by the grace of God kyng of Englande and of Fraunce, defender of the the fayth, lorde of Irelande, and in erth the supreme heed next and immediate vnder Christe of the Churche of Englande, with hartye prayse and thankes gyuyng vnto God for the same, / composed uppon the glad prophecy and ioyefull psalme of Benedictus dominus deus Israel. &amp;c..</title>
                  <author>Pylbarough, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[35] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>in ædibus Thomæ Bertheleti typis impress. Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum solum.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Londini :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno .M.D.XL..</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Initials.</note>
                  <note>Dedication heading gives author as John Pylbarough.</note>
                  <note>Place and publisher from colop.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴ D⁶.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Luke I, 68-79 --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:183786:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:183786:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A COMMEMO<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>RATION OF THE INES<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIMABLE GRACES AND BENEFITES OF GOD, INFVSED THROVGH THE</hi> bryght lyght of the knowlege of his holy word, in our moſte dradde ſoueraygne lorde <hi>HENRY</hi> the eyght, by the grace of god kyng of <hi>ENG<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LANDE</hi> and of <hi>FRAVNCE,</hi> defender of the fayth, lorde of Irelande, and in erth the ſupreme heed next and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate vnder <hi>CHRISTE</hi> of the Churche of Englande, with hartye prayſe and thankes gyuyng vn to <hi>GOD</hi> for the ſame, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the glad prophecy and ioyefull pſalme of <hi>Benedictus domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus deus Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>ANNO. M. D. XL.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:183786:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:183786:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RYGHT HONO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RABLE THOMAS LORDE CRVMVVEL knyght of the noble order of the Garther, lorde ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the priuy ſeale of our moſt ſouerayn lord the kyng, and alſo vicegerent of the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualtie, your humble and faythfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunt, Iohn Pylbarough deſyreth long helth and proſperous per ſeuerance in honour.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>ONSIDERYNGE</hi> often ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes in my ſelfe, (my ſyngular good lorde) the ineſtimable gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and benefytes, with the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che god of his infinite goodnes hath moſte largely indewed our moſte ſouerayne lorde the kynges mooſte noble maieſtie, wherof his grace hath abundantly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted alſo vnto vs his mooſte humble and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge ſubiectes, by the illuſtration of goddis moſte holy worde, and vnto what conſolation, ioye, and comforet, from oure longe peynefully ſuffered thraldome, dreadefulle darkenes, and daungers of our bodies, ſoules, and all that we had beſydes forth, we be nowe moſt bleſſedly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuered and comme, throughe the ſame, I haue thought and yet aſſuredly do thynke, there is no faythfull or true englyſhe hart, that can reteyne and kepe to hym ſelfe the memoriall therof, and not erneſtly and with al diligence indeuour and apply hym ſelfe, by all ſuche meanes and ways,
<pb facs="tcp:183786:3"/>
as his wytte power and counnynge, whiche god hath gyuen hym, wylle ſerue hym, to vtter and ſet forthe the ſame, bothe to the condigne laude and prayſe of god therfore, and vnto the perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall renowne and gloriouſe fame of our ſayde moſte ſoueraygne lorde, as the very miniſter, in and by whome <hi>GOD</hi> hathe thus wonderfully wrought in vs, and as in whom (as Paul ſaith) our reioyſynge myght abounde and increaſe by <note place="margin">Philipp. 1.</note> Ieſu Chriſte, by reaſon of his returne home a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne to his right and iuſte title of godly mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration and power ouer vs, wherof he, and his moſte noble progenytours, haue ben vniuſtely, by vſurpacion, longe depriued. Wherevpon for my part, in diſcharge of my conſcience and due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie towardes god &amp; his maieſtie in this behalfe, I haue applyed my beſt wyll (accordynge to my <note place="margin">Matth. 25.</note> litell, and not vnknowen to all men moſte leaſt) gyfte, whiche I haue thankefully (notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge) receyued of god amongeſt other, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowe and employe to his vſe, to compyle this lyttell treatyſe, vpon the ioyfull pſalme, <hi>Benedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus dominus deus Iſrael. &amp;c.</hi> the glad prophecye and <note place="margin">Luc. 1.</note> prayſegyuynge vnto god by zachary, whiche by interpretation is aſmoch to ſay, as remembring god, of and for the vniuerſall ſpirituall viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and redemption of mankynde, by Chriſtis becommynge incarnate, and commendation of his choſen myniſter thervnto, Iohn Baptiſte: wherof and of whoſe conception alſo he was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>opinable at the tyme of the reuelation therof, by
<pb facs="tcp:183786:3"/>
reaſon of the very old ages of him and his wife, to thente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the ſame, which I wold to god were as effectuouſly ſhewed and ſet forth by me herin, as I haue bothe hartily and faythfully pourpoſed and ment it, myght be an occaſion and example for vs, bothe to laude and prayſe god of and for our ſpecyal viſytation and redemption, through the lyght of goddis moſt holy worde, wherof we were alſo inopinable and faytheleſſe at the fyrſte pronouncynge thereof, by reaſon that the ſame was longe hydde from vs, and mannes tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and inuentions crepte betwene. And alſo to commende worthely our ſayd moſt ſouerayne lorde, goddes holy miniſter therof, in perpetuall memory, and from generation of vs into gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, leſte we whiche as adoptiue Iſraelytes by faythe do preſently enioye ſo hyghe and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly benefytes by god and his ſayde mynyſter the kynges maieſtie, ſhulde be accompted any leſſe thankefull therfore, then was zacharie, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſatisfied with only hope, thanked and prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God and his holy mynyſter Iohn Baptiſte, for the merites of Chriſtes incarnation, then to come. Whyche Treatiſe moſte temeraryouſly I haue dedycate vnto you, whom I haue always eſtemed, lyke the ryght vertuous and faythfull Saphan, vnto his moſte godly prynce Ioſias, a gracious fauourer of all honeſt and holy pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, and my very ſyngular good lorde: Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtynge that although bothe for the groſſe hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge of ſo fyne a matter, and alſo the rude and
<pb facs="tcp:183786:4"/>
inornate ſtyle and phraſe therof, it be nothynge worthy ſuche preferrement in dede, yet neuer the leſſe your accuſtomed benignite wyl vouchſafe to reform the ſame, wherin it may ſeme vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you conuenient, &amp; alſo accept and make it worthye, agreinge to my good wyl intended ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. And for my parte, I ſhall not onely moſt hartly prayſe and thanke god therfore, but alſo accordinge to my bounden duetie owe vnto your good lordeſhyppe my harty prayer and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſeruyce whyle I lyue.</p>
            <closer>GOD SAVE THE KYNGE</closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:183786:4"/>
            <head>¶Benedictus dominus deus Iſrael: quia ui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitauit &amp; fecit Redemptionem plebis ſue.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>OR AS MOCHE AS</hi> in the Scryptures of the olde Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and the newe, it is no rare thyng, that dyuerſe perſons ben named ſome before their birthes &amp; ſome when they haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued with one name, haue had the ſame cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged, accor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dinge &amp; for ſuche occaſions or qualities as haue ryſen or ben in them, or for ſome ſynguler mery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes gyuen vnto them (whereof to make an hole reherſall, it were no leſſe to my capacytie impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyble, than to your readyng tedious) I am and dare be bolde (without offence to any perſon) for the godly occaſion and vertuous qualities (whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che nowe ben apparant in vs moſte chriſtian en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glyſhe people) to repute and aſcribe worthyly to vs the name of Iſraelites. For lyke as Iacob, <note place="margin">Geneſ. 25.</note> whiche is as moche to ſay, as a ſupplanter, was an apte name for hym, accordyng to his qualitie than, bycauſe he had ſupplanted his brother E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau, <note place="margin">Gene. 27.</note> both of his byrthright and fathers bleſſing, wherfore Eſau ſayd of hym, he may wel be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Iacob, for he hath twyſe vndermynded me, and Eſaus name was chaunged into Edom, as who ſhuld ſay (redde) by cauſe he hadde ſolde the ſaide byrthright for a meace of redde meate, as lyke apte a name was after for the ſame Iacob <note place="margin">Geneſ. 32.</note> (Iſraell) whiche is interpreted, a man ſeinge
<pb facs="tcp:183786:5"/>
the lorde) by cauſe he had ſene god and his won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 28. <hi>Pſal</hi> 113. <hi>Exod.</hi> 12. <hi>Exod.</hi> 13.</note> heauenly ſyghtes. Whiche Iſraell and his generation god chaſe to hym a peculiar peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, &amp; in them extended his holyneſſe &amp; ſtrength, and ſaued theym in Egypte, from the greuous plague through the bloudde of the lambe. And for them Chriſt ſayd alſo, I came not but to cure <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 15.</note> the ſhepe of the houſe of Iſrael, that were peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed: Euen ſo bycauſe we now ſe the lord god by his ſcriptures and by his holy worde, be ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed &amp; ſtrengthed in hym, and ſpirituallye cured through the blod of our redemer Chriſt, we may ryght well &amp; aptly be callyd Iſraelites, a people ſeing god, a people ſanctified and ſtrengthed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſai.</hi> 62. <hi>Et uoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunt eos populus ſanctus, re dempti a domino. Titum.</hi> 2.</note> goddis worde, &amp; cured with Chriſtis bloud. For the grace of god our ſauyour hath appered vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, and openynge the eyes of our vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng, hath taught vs to ſee and knowe Chriſte. Fantaſies nor dremes, mens inuentions do not nowe blynde or deceyue vs any longer. For the brode buſſhell of hypocriſye, whiche ouerwhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the bryght candell (goddis worde) is nowe taken away, and we ſee all ouer the houſe of our owne conſciences: and we ſe thauctour of light, and the very lyght it ſelfe, that lyghteneth (with diuerſitie of graces) all reſonable creatures co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynge <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioan.</hi> 1.</note> into this worlde. And whom (although he was in the worlde) we beinge ſeduced and led blyndefulle by vanities, coulde not perceyue or knowe tylle nowe at the laſte, whyle we were a people wandrynge in darknes of ignorance, and
<pb facs="tcp:183786:5"/>
dwellers in the ſhadowes of dethe, which is ſyn, accompanyed with deathe: the greate lyghte of goddis moſt holy word dyd appere vnto vs, and <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſai.</hi> 9. <hi>Roma.</hi> 13.</note> our redemption was nerer tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we were aware. And where we were before in darknes, a people ignorant of god, we be nowe inlyghtened with <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.</note> the bryghtnes of knowledge in our lorde god: who hath commanded the lyght to ſhyne out of darknes, whiche hath ſhyned in our hartes, for to gyue the lyght of the knowledge of the glorye of god in the face of Ieſus Chriſt, that is in the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 16.</note> faithe, whiche Peter and his felowe apoſtles by hym, one anſwerynge for all, confeſſed in Chriſt to be the ſonne of the lyuynge god. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon which Chriſt, and fayth in hym, and vpon, or in none other, our catholyke congregation immediatly is firmely ſettled. Lette vs therfore nowe, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge receyued this lyght of god, imprynte the memoriall therof in our hartes, with perfect be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefe therof, &amp; magnifie god therfore, that it may fructifie in vs good workes, and make vs bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed through the ſame, before all nations, as was the holy virgyn Mary by Eliſabeth, ſaying vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her, Bleſſed arte thou amonge women, and <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 1.</note> bleſſed is the fruite of thy wombe. For bycauſe thou haſte mekely receyued the holye worde of god, and gladde tydynges by his angell: Thoſe ſame thynges ſhall be perfourmed in the, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge as the ſame aungell hath ſayde vnto the. And alſo by example of Zachary, who bycauſe he beleued not the poſſibilitie of goddis worde,
<pb facs="tcp:183786:6"/>
whiche the aungell dydde ſhewe vnto hym, was <note place="margin">Luc. 1.</note> made ſpecheles for a tyme, but whan he ſaw the perfection therof, beinge ſory for his infidelitie, dydde receyue ageyne by goddis goodneſſe, his ſpeche, augmented with the grace and ſpirite of prophecienge and thankes gyuynge vnto god for the ſame: being repentant and deteſtyng, that we haue ben ſo longe mysbeleuyng of the word of god, ſhewed and ſet forthe vnto vs by goddis holy doctours and prechers, whom the Sathan of Rome hath dyuelliſhly tormented, burnt, and ſlayne, to kepe vs faithles, and make vs dumbe, that we ſhulde not blowe out his errours and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes, nor kynges &amp; temporall rulers ſhulde be lerned of their godly auctorities ouer their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes (whyche the ſame Sathan had vſurped) let vs nowe, not lyke as the tenne, whiche were <note place="margin">Luce. 17.</note> healed of their leprie, wherof one onely came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geyn to gyue thankes to God, but holly and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tierly togythers, euen as the thre whiche were in the forneys of fyre, lauded and glorifyed god, as <note place="margin">Daniel. 3.</note> it had ben with one mouth, braſt out like the day ſpryng the lyght of the faythe that is in vs, and reioyſyng in the byrth of Iohn, that is in the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly goſpell newe ryſen amongeſt vs by the grace of god, prayſe and thanke moſt hartily with Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chary our lorde god of Iſraell, whiche hath vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyted <note place="margin">Benedictus dominus de us Iſrael qui a uiſitauit &amp; fecit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>edem ptionem ple bis ſuae.</note> vs, illumynyng our feble ignorant hartes with the knowlege of his moſt holy word. Wher by he hath cauſed the redemption of vs his pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culyar people, from our thrall captiuitie of our
<pb facs="tcp:183786:6"/>
goſtely ennemy the deuyll, and our both gooſtly and bodyly ennemye, the byſſhop of Rome, and his complyces.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>ET erexit cornu ſalutis nobis in domo Dauid pueri ſui.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ANTICHRIST</hi> of Rome hath longe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimuled with vs, foodynge vs forthe with vanities: As pardons, pilgrimages, bulles, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ryght calued, ſuperſticions, counterfeite re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, feyned relyques, and ſuche other innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable ſort of traſhes, haberdaſhery ware, and all for money. For the old prouerbe, <hi>Omnia vena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia Rome,</hi> ſayd by the Pagans, long before Chriſt <note place="margin">Saluſtius.</note> was incarnate, is not lefte vnpractiſed by the ſayde Antichriſt our moſte holy father (as they call hym) his cardinalles and byſhoppes. wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the chiefe marchaunt of myſchiefe is the ſayd holy father. I praye you, what thynge was and yet is not ſale kynde at Rome, ſauinge our en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glyſhe ſoules: for the whiche we haue nowe of late founde a better marte? And that whiche is moſt abhorred of god, the ſayd Antichriſte, and moſte aduerſary of Chriſt, had brought vs into the ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tils worſhipping of fals goddis. Oh god of Iſrael, for thy tender mercy, into what blynd fantaſies of madde myſchiefe were we thy ſelye creatures brought by the hydynge and ſhutting vp of thy holy worde from vs? And what iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries dyd thy moſte faythfull miniſters, and yet for the moſt parte do ſuſteyne, to be ſo arrogant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:183786:7"/>
depriued of theyr princely regymentes vnder the, by thambycious wraſtyng of thy ſayd word to the mayntenaunce of a dyuellyſhe power a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt thy ryght power? wherby the due obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of ſubiectes was conuerted into rebellion, and the concord of commonties diſſolued: Thou layeſt good god, as thou haddeſt ben a ſlepe, and dyd ſuffer vs to dreame by the, Euen as thou dyddeſt from Adams fall, vnto the tyme thy on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſonne became incarnate, wherof zachary pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecied a lyttell before, ſaying, That thou had<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt rayſed vp an horne for our helthe, meaning, <note place="margin">Et erexit cornu ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis nobis In domo Dauid pue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i ſui.</note> that Chryſt ſhuld be borne the vniuerſal ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth power and glorye of our ſaluation, and that in the houſe of kynge Dauid thy electe ſeruaunte. But nowe through the lyght, whiche is ſprong in vs, vpon thy holy worde, (agaynſt an vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped power and reigne of Lucifer, moſte vntrue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly counterfayte, vpon thy moſt vndouted trewe worde) thou haſt rayſed vp to vs thy peculyas people, a godly dewe power of helthe, our natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall moſt ſoueraygne lorde kynge <hi>HENRY</hi> the <hi>VIII.</hi> by thy grace, which is alſo a true ſtrength and ryghtfull kyngedome, apperteynyng to the moſte noble houſe of his moſte famouſe proge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitours, for our great conſolation, tranquillite, and holſome ſafetie, bothe of our bodyes and ſoules to. Whoſe maieſtie we recogniſe and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue throughe thy ſayde worde, to be thyne holy enoynted, immediate minyſter, and vicar ouer <note place="margin">Roma. 13. 1. Petri. 2. Sapien, 6.</note> vs: and vnto whom onelye thy goodnes hath
<pb facs="tcp:183786:7"/>
commytted the cure charge and gouernaunce of vs, and whom we owe to obey loue and dreade, and to whom alſo we owe only to haue recourſe as vnto thy chiefe herdeman. But alas we haue <note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.</note> ben longe (yea and to longe) wandrynge frome hym, and haue ſought a ſtrange ſhepherde, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſemynge vnto vs as meke and humble as a lambe, (what by him ſelfe and what by his whel pes) hath bene a very deuourynge wulfe of vs, and more rauenouſe then a wulfe. for he hath not onely conſumed the ſhepe, but the flece and bones alſo. But nowe being retourned home a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne by the diligente ſerche and labour of our <note place="margin">1. Petri. 2.</note> ſayde moſte louynge kynde and holy paſtour, let vs not erre nor ſtraye agayne from hym, for he is lothe to loſe one the worſte of vs, lette vs not then loſe hym, but mooſte kyndely folowe hym, ſtycke by him, defende hym, obeye hym, and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyngely dreade and honour hym, euen for god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des ſake, and for conſcience ſake, bycauſe god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des <note place="margin">Roma. 13.</note> holy word teacheth and byndeth vs ſo to do.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶Sicut locutus eſt per os ſanctorum: qui à ſeculo ſunt prophetarum eius.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>CHRISTE VVAS</hi> not ſodeynly borne, but his incarnation and commyng to be borne in the houſe of Dauid, was ſpoken of god, by the mouthes of his prophetes, from the begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge of the worlde: that we ſhulde faythfully beleue it. And therfore vndoubtedly Ieremie, Daniel, Eſais, Micheas, zacharie, and all the <note place="margin">Hiere. 23. Daniel. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:183786:8"/>
reſidue of the prophetes ceſſed not, to prophecye <note place="margin">Eſai. 11. Miche. 5. Zacha. 6.</note> and ſhewe Chriſtes incarnation. And the ſame alſo dyd the dedes of Adam, Abel, Enoch, and of al other the fathers of the olde teſtament ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyfeſtly ſet forth: as vndoubtedly alſo doth the ſame fathers, and prophetes, and other the reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due of the olde teſtament, if due application be put therunto, partely by theyr dedes, and parte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note place="margin">Eſai. 14. Ezec. 22. 23. 24. 34. Hiere. 29. Daniel. 12.</note> by theyr prophecies, bothe ſhewe and ſet forth the pompous pride and vſurpatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the byſhop of Rome, and the miſchiefes captiuities and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominations that haue enſued thervpon to god des flocke. and yet the ſame byſhoppes, captay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of al thoſe myſchiefes, neyther haue nor ſhal eſcape quyte awaye: for vtter confuſion, depe falles, and perpetual damnation, both hath and ſhall, as ſure as god lyueth, come vppon theyr neckes therfore. And the ſame fathers and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes <note place="margin">3. Re. 10. 3. Reg. 1. 2. Par. 29. 2. Para. 30. 2. Para. 31. 2. Para. 23.</note> do lyke wyſe ſhewe and ſet forthe, that of very godly ryghte and iuſtice, kynges prynces and other temporall rulers, euer from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynnynge of the worlde, haue and oughte to be the only gouernours orderers and rulers of and ouer theyr people, naturally broughte vp, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregate, <note place="margin">2. Par. 34. Sap<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 6.</note> and beinge within theyr prouynces re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>almes and dominions, of what ſo euer ſorte de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree <note place="margin">4. Re. 17.</note> or condicion they be, ſpirituall or temporal, as we cal them: And what honourable and hum <note place="margin">2. re. 18. 19 3. Reg. 1.</note> ble obedyence the ſubiectes of euery kynde and ſorte, owe to vſe and beare towardes theyr kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges <note place="margin">Daniel. 4.</note> and rulers, and that god was the onely ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:183786:8"/>
vp and putter downe of them: And that god <note place="margin">1. Regum. 15. 16. 3. Reg. 2.</note> toke, and aſſuredly wyl take, ſore and greuouſe vengeaunce vpon ſuch, as dyſturbed the royall ſeate of any kynge or prynce: And howe gracy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſely <note place="margin">1. Reg. 10.</note> alſo god doth preſerue kynges and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, infuſynge in them ſpeciall godly gyftes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue other. And the ſayde fathers and prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes <note place="margin">1. Reg. 15.</note> do warne and exhorte the ſubiectes, inceſſant ly to praye for theyr kynges prynces and rulers. All which prophecies and dedes of the ſayd pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes and fathers, Chriſte hym ſelfe, after his commyng, affyrmeth, and by his owne moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly word and examples doth teache and ſtraight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bynde vs, to doo and folowe the ſame. For he beinge of two differente natures, that is bothe god and man, and beinge kynge of kynges, and the ſupreme power, as he ſaythe in the laſte cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter of Matth. Al power is gyuen to me in hea <note place="margin">Matth. ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timo.</note> uen and in erthe. In heauen, bycauſe he had it ſo, as god, before he was incarnate: In erthe, bycauſe he was god and man after his incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and refuſynge and deteſtynge all worldly honour and kyngedome, chargynge alſo Peter, and all his true folowers, to do lykewyſe, dydde moſt humbly meke hym ſelfe, and takyng vpon <note place="margin">Philipp. 2.</note> hym the faſhion of a ſeruaunt, was wyllyngely moſte poore and mooſte obedient ſubiecte to the worldly powers. For he ſayth of hym ſelfe. The <note place="margin">Luc. 9.</note> foxes haue dennes, &amp; the byrdes of the ayre haue neſtes, but the ſonne of man hath not wherin to thruſt his heed. And his obedience was ſo great,
<pb facs="tcp:183786:9"/>
as none coulde be more. For he was obedient vn to his fathers wyll, and to worldly powers wyl, alſo euen vnto the moſte ſhamefull death of the <note place="margin">Luce. 23.</note> croſſe, by the iudgement of the ruler Ponce Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late. And to ſette forthe this obedience with all, Chriſte teacheth vs a leſſon vpon the reſolution of the perfydous and fraudulent queſtyon, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded of hym by the meſſangers of the chief of the ſcribes and phariſeys, whiche Luke reher <note place="margin">Luc. 20.</note> ſeth in the .xx. chapiter, Whether it be laufull to gyue tribute to Ceſar or no. To whiche Chriſte anſwered thus in effect, yelde to Ceſar that whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is Ceſars, and to god that which is goddis. As who ſayth, bycauſe your temporall ruler and ſoueraygne lorde, hath power ouer your bodyes and goodis, and is your defender and preſeruer, and alſo charged in his ſpiritual miniſtery with you vnder god: yelde to hym tribute, a knowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege of your ſubiection. And bicauſe god gyueth you body and ſoule, and al that ye haue beſydes <note place="margin">Deuter. 6. Matth. 22.</note> forth, and hath power ouer all, and aſketh no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge but your ſoule for all: yelde hym that.</p>
               <p>¶ And Chriſte an other tyme to verify his ſayd <note place="margin">Luc. 21.</note> pouertie, and for an example of obedience, that his true folowers ſhulde beare to the temporalle powers, he commaunded Peter, to take moneye out of a fyſhes mouth, bycauſe neyther of them <note place="margin">Matt. 17.</note> had any, to pay to the gatherer for theym bothe. Peter alſo taught of Chriſt to ſet forth this obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, <note place="margin">1. <hi>Petri.</hi> 2.</note> gaue commandement to all the faythful, to be obedient for goddis ſake to the kyng, as to
<pb facs="tcp:183786:9"/>
the chief hed, &amp; to other his ſubſtitute rulers &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties: And Paule co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth the ſame, addyng <note place="margin">Roma. 13.</note> thervnto, that euery power is of god, &amp; is goddis miniſter, &amp; not otherwiſe, and the reſiſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce therof is damnation. And Paule wrytynge to Titus, <note place="margin">Titum. 3.</note> byddeth hym to charge the people, to obey prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis, and the hygher powers. And Peter, Paule, <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.</note> and other the appoſtels, call them ſelfes in holye ſcriptures but minyſters, and theyr power a my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterye. And accordyng to this, Peter was obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyent in myniſtrynge at the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement of the <note place="margin">Galath. 2.</note> other apoſtelles, to goo to Samarie with Iohn. And alſo Peter was appoynted to be a preacher amonge the Iewes, and Iohn and Iames with hym: &amp; Paule and Barnabas with hym, among the gentyles. And Paule boſteth, that Peter and Iohn gaue hym their right handes. And Paule ſayth alſo, that he blamed Peter openly, bycauſe he folowed not the trouthe of the goſpel. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable mo auctorities of ſcripture are to be reherſed hereof. But nowe, leſte I ſhoulde ſeme to longe in this place, let this lyttell pretye piece, though it were moche leſſe, cut out of the ryghte large, true wrought, and moſte beautyfull cloth, goddis holy ſcriptures, concerning the Iudaical Antichriſt of Rome, and his adherentes, whyche ſtande beſt in their owne pernyciouſe conceytes, lyke the Iewes, whoſe blyndnes cauſed them to beleue Iohn Baptiſt, better then Chriſt, not with ſtandyng the greate nomber of ſygnes and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies, whiche they had, witneſſing that he was
<pb facs="tcp:183786:10"/>
come, be ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to lay before them, for a patron, to ſtayne and vtterly ſhame all their counterfayt clothes of fals interpretations, and coloured glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes of their feyned goſpel. And thanke our lorde god of Iſrael, that he hath ſo clered our ſyght, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we haue now at the laſt, found a right Paul, our ſayd moſt ſouerayn lord the kyng, to comptroll &amp; abolyſhe Peters diſſimuled ſucceſſours counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayte goſpell, and to auaunce, and preferre god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis owne moſt true and faythfull goſpell.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Salutem ex inimicis noſtris, &amp; de manu omnium qui oderunt nos.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>OVR AVNCIENT</hi> enmy, who bycauſe he had ben ſo high a creature, aboue other, and become from an angell of highe heauen, a deuyll <note place="margin">Eſai. 14.</note> in depe hell, for that that he wold haue ben equal with the higheſt, neuer ceaſſed after to ſtryue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geynſt god, and his beſt beloued creature man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynde. In ſo moche, that ſo ſone as euer he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued the fyrſt parentes were formed and ſetlyd in the pleaſant place of Paradyſe, &amp; that god had bounde them to a certayne obedience, he infected <note place="margin">Gen. 3.</note> them with his peſtilent pride of diſobedience a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geynſt god, for the whiche they were exyled that place, and both they and theyr poſteritie brought to rume and captiue bondes of the ſame ennemy and his innumerable ſort of euyll angels, which contynually laye in awayte of theym, vntyll the birth of Chriſte, who was and is the vnyuerſall horne power ſtrength and glory, for the helth of
<pb facs="tcp:183786:10"/>
mankynde, againſt the ſayd enemy, and his ſayd aungelles, whiche yet neuertheleſſe deſiſteth not day and nyght, nor neuer wyll accordynge to his olde cuſtome, by a thouſand ingyns and meanes to plant debate betwene god and man, &amp; betwene man and man, power and power, &amp; euery where cauſeth diſobedience, and rebellion of ſubiectes, ageynſt their ſouerains, &amp; ledeth mankind by fan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taſies &amp; illuſions from one miſchiefe to an other, vntyll he brynge them to forgette god, and vnto what order they were appoynted fyrſt by god, as by experic<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce amongeſt our ſelfes, here in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d we haue cauſe beſt to perceyue. For what by oure ſayd enmye the deuyll, and what by our ennemy the byſhoppe of Rome, his traditions and fals doctrynes, his vanities and dreames, his hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie and fayned relygion, the dyuels ſnares, we were brought in caſe, that we dyd ſet more by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> than by god, or any part of his doctrine, ana fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red more the byſſhop of Romes curſe, than god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis vengeaunce, whiche began to come in hande apace by the moſte contagious plagues of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions and rebellions amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt our ſelfes. But <note place="margin">Salutem</note> that god, whiche is the inlyghtner of the harte of man, and the helthe of mans ſoule, of his ineſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable mercy and goodnes, rayſed vp for vs his power of helth of glory and of ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, our godly Ioſias, and moſte ſoueraygne lorde the kynges maieſtie, to wake and conſyder vs his corrupt &amp; wandrynge flocke, and hauynge receyued by the handes of his ryght vertuous ſcrybe Saphan, <note place="margin">2. <hi>Par.</hi> 34.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:183786:11"/>
euen the grace of god, the boke of the law of god long hid, did ſet forth the ſame with al diligence, by which our ignorant darknes is become a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect knowlege of lyght, And we perceyue clerely, that we dyd abuſe our ſelfes in diſobedience both ageynſt god, and our ſayd ſouerayn lorde, whom god hath ordeyned oure Michaell, our Dauyd, <note place="margin">Ex inimicis noſtris,</note> and our only helth in erth, ageynſt the pompous Lucifer, and monſtruous Golyath of Rome, and all our enemyes of euery ſort, and who is an able power and ſtrengthe by god, to defende and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue <note place="margin">Et de manu omniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> qui oderu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t nos. Pſal. 88.</note> vs, from the handes of all theym that hate vs. For god ſayth of him, I haue put helpe in the power, and man of myghte, and haue auaunced, whome I haue choſen among my people, I haue founde Dauid myn owne ſeruant, whom I haue annoynted with my holye oyle. And therfore my hande ſhall helpe hym, and myn arme ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme hym, his ennemye ſhall not preuayle at all in hym, and the chyld of iniquitie ſhall not preaſe to hurt hym, I ſhal make his enmyes fall downe by heapes before his face, and ſhall put to flyght ſuche as hate hym, my trouth and mercy ſhall be euer with hym, and in my name ſhal his horne of of glory, power, and helth, be exalted. Lo, this is moſt comfortable helth, conſolation, reioyce, and glorie of all faythfull louynge hartes, and moſte terrible feare, quakynge dreade, and vtter confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of all vntrue, malicious, and hatefull tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours: whiche are goddis and our moſte deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and abhorrible ennemies and haters.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:183786:11"/>
               <head>Ad faciendam miſericordiam cum patribus noſtris, &amp; memorari teſtamenti ſui ſancti: Iusiurandum quod iurauit ad Abraham pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trem noſtrum daturum ſe nobis.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ZACHARIE PRAYSETH GOD,</hi> that by the horne of power and helthe, whiche he hath rayſed vp for vs in the houſe of Dauid (as is before mencioned) he ſhulde do and ſhewe his mercy with the fathers, Abraham Iſaac Iacob, <note place="margin">Ad facien da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> miſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> patribus noſtris.</note> and all the other of the olde teſtamente, that they beinge deade before Chryſtes commynge, ſhulde be part takers with theyr children and folowers, of the benefytes of his paſſion, wherin they had perfyte hope whyle they lyued. And he byndeth god thervnto in the true performance of his moſt <note place="margin">Geneſ. 15. Et memo rari teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti ſui ſancti, Ius iuran. &amp;c.</note> holy couenaunt that he promyſed Abraham: The mooſte bleſſed vyrgine Marie beinge conceyued with Chryſte alſo (as in the ſame fyrſte chapyter of Luke is reherſed) magnifieth god moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly for the ſame, after this maner, That all that is in her doth magnifie god, bycauſe he hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde the mekenes of his hande mayde, whom al nations ſhall bleſſe. For his myghte hath doone <note place="margin">Luc. 1.</note> great thynges to her, and therfore his name is holy, and his mercy is infinite, for he hath not on ly ſhewed it in her, but frome generation to gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, ſuche as feare hym. he hath taken vp his ſeruaunt Iſrael, beinge remembred of his holye couenante, accordyng as he promyſed Abraham, and his ſeede for euer more. Whiche Mary and zacharie bothe, enforce vs nowe alſo (as trewe
<pb facs="tcp:183786:12"/>
Iſraelytes and ſeers of god) to magnyfie and prayſe our lorde god of Iſrael, for his great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and holy couenant late ſhewed and performed in vs. For lyke as it is alſo wrytten. That there fel an heuy ſlepe vpon Abraham, and gret darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes <note place="margin">Geneſ. 15.</note> fell vpon hym. And the lord ſayde vnto him, knowe this of a ſuertye, that thy ſeede ſhall be a ſtraunger in a lande that is not theyrs. And they ſhall make bondemen of them, and intreate them euyll, foure hundred yeres, but the people, whom they ſhall ſerue, wyll I iudge, afterwarde they ſhall go forthe with great ſubſtaunce. Euen ſoo was it come to paſſe with vs, for our fathers and alſo we beinge ſeduced and led blynde with fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſies and mens inuentions, by the ſubtyle pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of the ambicyouſe Romanyſte Lucifer, and his complices, were caſte into an heuy ſlepe, and great darkenes of ignoraunce in god, and his mooſte holy worde, and therby alſo were we as ſubtylly and ſlylye conueyed, and made captyue ſtraungers at Rome, bycauſe we had of ryghte nothynge to do in that citie or lande, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore were we euyll intreated of them, with theyr myſchiefes and abhominations accordyngelye, And as men vſe theyr bondemen, ſoo vſed they vs. For they ſet vs beſyly and vylye a worke, to clyme the ladder, to brynge them word what god dyd in heauen, but the more we dydde clyme, the farther downe we wente, And then we muſt ſeke this ſaynte, and that ſaynte, this blocke and that ſtocke, this toye and that toye, offer here and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer
<pb facs="tcp:183786:12"/>
there, and kyſſe here and lycke there, tylle it was tyme to reſte for werynes. The Egipcian ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannye was neuer more laborous to our forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. And what ſo euer we coulde get or gather together was ſhortly after theyr owne good, and had nothing therfore but cleane remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thrift. And neyther wold they manumiſe one of vs, but take our cheuage and let vs go tyll a nother time &amp; gather more. And this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> foure hundred yeres, vntyll our lorde god of Iſraell, whoſe ineſtimable mercy and goodnes, whoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enarable ryghtuouſeneſſe and trouth excedeth al thynge that is, vouchedſafe of late tyme to illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myne moſte graceouſely our ſayd darkenes, with his holy word, wherby we haue perceyued Chriſt the auctour of our lyght, and our onely ſauiour, to be as it were newly come and incarnate for vs: and that throughe the fayth whiche we haue in hym, we be (as Paule ſayth) reputed iuſtified as <note place="margin">Galath. 3. Roma. 4.</note> was our father Abraham, whoſe chyldren adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue and multiplication of his ſede by faythe, we nowe alſo be. And the very partetakers with our ſayde forefathers Abraham Iſaac Iacob, and al the remanaunt of the olde teſtamente and newe bothe, and they with vs, of the merytes of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes bloud, promyſed by god to Abraham and his ſayde ſede for euermore, to whom the bloudde of a lambe was a figuratiue ſaluation in Egypte. <note place="margin">Exod. 12.</note> And we perceyue alſo, by the illumination of the ſayde holy worde, that the byſhoppe of Rome, to whoſe tyranny we were thus as is ſayde, thrall,
<pb facs="tcp:183786:13"/>
is iudged of god, to be Chryſtes vtter aduerſary, and the vſurper of the ryghtful power of kynges and prynces, goddes ryghte myniſters ouer his people. And we newely adoptiue Iſraelites from <note place="margin">Exod. 12. 13. 14.</note> the ſayde thraldome of the ſayd byſhop, through the ſame worde alſo, no leſſe wonderfully delyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red into great welthe and ioye by our moſt godly captayn the kynges highnes, then were our fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father Iſraelites from the captiuitie of the tyran nous Pharao into the pleſaunt land of promiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by theyr holy prophete and leader Moyſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Vt ſine timore de manu inimicorum noſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum liberati ſeruiamus illi: In ſanctitate &amp; iuſticia coram ipſo omnibus diebus noſtris.</head>
               <p>SITHENS through thonly ineſtimable good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, <note place="margin">Vt ſine ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more de manu ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micorum noſtroru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> liberati</note> mercy, and loue of god towarde vs, and not by any part of our deſeruyng towardes him, we be thus graciouſly carcleſſe and without any feare delyuered, from the handes of our before reherſed ennemies, and are become the ſeers of god, and the adoptyue chyldren of Abraham by faythe, through the illumination of his moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly worde in vs, and conuerted from the nyght in to the daye, that is from the darkenes of the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant knowlege of god to the bryght knowlege <note place="margin">Seruiamꝰ illi.</note> of hym: it behoueth vs with all our mynde with all our harte, with all our ſoule, and with al that which is or may be in vs, to loue and dreade him, and with pure and ſincere holynes and faythfull <note place="margin">In ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate &amp; iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticia,</note> ryghtuouſenes, ſerue and honour hym, lyke as
<pb facs="tcp:183786:13"/>
Paule ſayth, god hath not called vs to lyue im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purely, <note place="margin">Roma. 12.</note> but to lyue holyly, not to faſſhion our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fes vnto this worlde, but to be changed through the renewyng of our mynde. And therfore Paule <note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.</note> byddeth vs to be the folowers of god, as mooſte derely beloued chyldren, and to walke in loue as Chryſte loued vs. And puttynge vs in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce, that we were ſometyme darkenes, and nowe lyght in our lorde god, biddeth vs to walke as chyldren of the lyght. for the fruite of the ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite is all maner of rightuouſnes and trouth, and to proue what is pleaſynge vnto the lorde. And haue no felowſhyp with the vnfruitefull workes of darkenes, but rather rebuke them. And Peter alſo comfortyng vs in our choſen generation, our <note place="margin">1. <hi>Petri.</hi> 2.</note> holy nation, and that we be a peculiar peple, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs, that we ſhuld ſhewe the vertues of him, whiche hath called vs frome darkenes vnto his merueylouſe lyght, Euen we, whiche are nowe a people of god, whiche ſometyme were not ſo, and whiche nowe haue obteyned mercy, whiche ſome tyme we had not, and commaundeth vs to ſette a ſyde all vice, that they, whiche backebyte vs for euyl doers, maye ſe our good workes, and prayſe god in the day of viſitacion. And he there ſubioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth dyuers rules of good workes, of the which the fyrſte is, that we ſhoulde ſubmytte our ſelfes vnto all creatures for goddes ſake, whether it be vnto the kyng, as vnto the chiefe heade and moſt excellent aboue other, or vnto any other his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute rulers and deputies, which ar ſent by him,
<pb facs="tcp:183786:14"/>
for the puniſhement of the euyl, and prayſe of the good, for ſoo is the wyll of god. And briefely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt other he compileth this leſſon, Honour all men, loue brotherly felowſhyp, feare god, and honour the kynge. And our auctour of lyghte, Chryſte ſaythe of hym ſelfe, I am the lyght of the <note place="margin">Ioan. 8.</note> world, and who that foloweth me, walketh not in darkenes, but ſhall haue euerlaſtynge lyfe. And what ſhall be our common pathe ſayth he, but do <note place="margin">Matth. 7.</note> all ſuche thynges to other men, whiche ye wolde they ſhuld do vnto you. And that we ſhuld know our tyme of workynge, he byddeth vs to worke whyle we haue light, and leſt we alſo ſhuld ſpend our tyme of lyght vnprofytably (lyke as Paule warneth vs, that we ſhulde not receyue grace in <note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.</note> vayne) he thretneth vs by example to take it from vs, and to beſtowe it better vppon other. For he ſayth, A certayne ſeruant, to whome his mayſter had deliuered a portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of money to employ, hyd y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Luc. 19.</note> money, &amp; dyd nothing therwith: &amp; therfore whan his maſter came to haue accompt of him &amp; other, &amp; founde he had made no encreaſe therof, he bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med hym ſore, &amp; cauſed it to be taken from him, &amp; deliuered vnto one of his other ſeruantes, whom he had tried a profytable ſeruaunt. And therfore Paule ſaythe vnto vs, As ye haue receyued of <note place="margin">1. <hi>Teſ.</hi> 4.</note> vs, howe ye ſhulde walke &amp; pleaſe god, ſo walke that ye may encreaſe the more abundauntly. and as Peter ſaythe, yf you be good louers and folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers <note place="margin">1. <hi>Petri.</hi> 3.</note> of Chriſte, who can hurte you? And yet our ſeruyce muſte be ſuche as god alloweth holy and <note place="margin">Cora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ipſo</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:183786:14"/>
rightuous, orels it were better vndone. And ther fore Chriſt taught his electes, howe their ſeruice <note place="margin">Matth. 5.</note> and workes ſhuld be accepted of god, ſaying vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, ye are the lyght of the worlde, and men vſe not to lyght a candell, &amp; ouerwhelme it with a buſhell whan they haue done, but ſetteth it vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon a candelſtycke, that it may light al them that be in the howſe, euen ſo let your lyght ſhyne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men, that they maye ſee your good workes, and glorifie, whom? you? nay, but your father, whiche is in heuen. as who ſaith, you can or ſhall do no workes (ſeme they neuer ſo holy) that ſhall be accepted of god, that are not done for goddis honour but for your owne. For ſo dyd the hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite phariſeis ſet abrode the ſkyrtes of their gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, and vſyd al their doinges to be ſene and prayſed of men. But Peter byddeth vs ſanctifie ourlorde Chriſt in our hartes. And Paule alſo <note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet. 3. 1. Cor. 6. 1. Cor.</hi> 10.</note> ſaythe, Glorifie and beare god in your bodye. as who ſayth, Let al your outward good workes be inwardely for goddis ſake, and his glorie. But howe farre thynke ye our popyſſhe monkery and fryerye, and all other diſguyſed rables of euerye kynde of the fayned and popeholy relygion (whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che thanked be god for his grace. are in a good towardnes to be made out of our wayes for euer more) be and haue be differynge from Zacharies before reherſed holynes and rightuouſnes before god? ſurely as farre as betweene zacharies ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quayntance <note place="margin">Matth. 7.</note> and theirs. And therfore all though they cry in neuer ſo great a route, and vntyl they
<pb facs="tcp:183786:15"/>
be hoorſe, lorde lorde open for vs, and haue in ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo faſt, yet wyll heauen gates open neuer the more. For Chriſte wyll anſwere theym, I neither knowe your newe faſhioned apparayle, nor you, ye be not my ſhepe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſe of Iſrael, for whom I made my holy couenant, ye be the Idolaters, the gentyls, ye neuer receyued my goſpel, nor dyd my fathers will, ye imbraſed Antichriſtes goſpel, &amp; were thexecutours of his wyl, euen the workes of darknes and of deth, ambition, ſedition, vayn glorye, and ſuche lyke abhomynations. I loued and taught aboue all thinges pouertie and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, ye made a promyſe, &amp; ſware vayne othes, <note place="margin">Oſee. 10.</note> to folowe me in them, but you hated them for all that aboue all thynges. Hypocrites, ye promyſed gold, but ye payd fylthy thinges, you made your ſelfes poſſeſſioners and lordes of the earthe, and were ſedycious diſobeyours of myne ordynances and holy lawes made by myn elect mynyſter and right folower of the good Ioſias, whom you diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimuled <note place="margin">2. <hi>Par.</hi> 34.</note> your moſte ſoueraygne lord, bearing an vſurper in your corrupte boſomes, that he ſhuld redreſſe your idolatrie &amp; abhomynable faſhyons of vngodly lyuyng, &amp; to put to better vſes your treaſures and poſſeſſions, whyche you dyd enioy withoute iuſte title by me. I ſaye to you therfore yet ones ageyne, I knowe you not, get you hens <note place="margin">Matt. 7.</note> from me into damnation with al your iniquites. And not withſtandynge theſe, yet be there other thynges, wherby our holynes and rightuouſnes ar lykewyſe to be made perfect beforegod, which
<pb facs="tcp:183786:15"/>
we muſt alſo obſerue, as that there be no diuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of opinions amongeſt vs, but as Paule ſaith, that we drawe all one way, hauyng one loue, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge <note place="margin">Philipp. 2.</note> of one accorde and of one mynde, that there be nothyng done through ſtryfe and vaynglory, but through mekenes of mind, and in that, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto <note place="margin">Philipp. 3.</note> we are come, let vs procede by one rule. And it is alſo to be obſerued, that we boſt not vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of our goſtely renewynge in the lyghte of the <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.</note> knowlege of god, as who ſaithe, it came of oure <note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. <hi>Roma.</hi> 12.</note> ſelfes, leſte whyle we meaſure our ſelues by oure ſelues, and holde onely of our ſelfes, we vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande nothyng. And leſt perauenture, whyle we <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.</note> ſeme to ſtande, we fall ſodeynly or we be ware. It behoueth than therfore, that we eſteme our ſelfes as Paule eſtemeth hym ſelfe, and folowe his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample therin, ſaying. It is the grace of god, that <note place="margin">Philipp. 3.</note> I am ſuch a one as I am, I am not al redy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, but I folow, if I may co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehende that wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I am comprehended of Chriſt Ieſu. Brethern <note place="margin">Omnibus diebus no ſtris.</note> I count not my ſelfe yet that I haue gotten it: but one thing I ſay, I forget that whiche is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hynde, and ſtretche my ſelfe vnto that whiche is before, and preaſe vnto the marke appoynted, to opteyne the rewarde of the hygh callyng of god in Chriſte Ieſu. And alſo our holynes and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſneſſe muſte haue a durable contynuance in a ryghte perfection, and not for a tyme, or nowe good and than euyll, but all tymes good, ſo as it may be ſayd, goddes word was ſowen in a good <note place="margin">Luc 8. Matth. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> lande, which fruitefully abydeth to the full tyme
<pb facs="tcp:183786:16"/>
of harueſt, and not in ſtony grounde or amonge buſſhes, ſo that it may not fructifie and tary the full tyme. For what auayleth it to haue be neuer ſo longe counted noble, wyſe, or counnynge, and at the laſte, through wylfull ignoraunce and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate frowardnes (as we of late haue knowen many) to be condemned to ſhamefull deathe, and to be noted in perpetuall memory moſt wretched and moſte folyſhe? Or what auayleth a manne to haue lyued all his dayes in holynes and rightu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, and at the laſt moment of his lyfe, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue a myſchiefe, &amp; be damned for euermore? yet better it were to lyue longe euyl, &amp; dye wel, as dyd he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> honge on the ryght hande of Chriſte, then to lyue longe well, and dye euyll, as dydde Iudas, who was longe good after he was called, and yet dyed moſte myſerably. And therefore as Chriſte ſaith, perſeuer in goodnes, and thou ſhalt be ſure to be ſaued by Chriſtis deth. Let vs then, hauing continually before the eies of our hartes the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpekeable goodnes and mercy of god ſhewed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs through the lyght of his moſt holy worde, not onely ſerue and honour him, our ſelfe in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecte holynes and rightuouſneſſe before hym all our dayes, but ſo ſhewe and ſette forthe vnto out chyldren, and ſuche other as we haue in charge vnder god, howe great thinges god hath doone for vs newe Iſraelites, that they alſo, and frome generation to generation, maye lyke wyſe ſerue and honour hym for euer more.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:183786:16"/>
               <head>¶ <hi>Et tu puer propheta altiſsimi uocaberis: preibis enim ante facie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> domini, parare uias eius: Ad dandam ſcientiam ſalutis plebi e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius, in remiſsionem peccatoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eorum: Per uiſcera miſericordie dei noſtri, in quibus ui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitauit nos oriens ex alto: Illuminare his qui in tenebris &amp; in umbra mortis ſedent ad dirigendos pedes noſtros in uiam pacis.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>LYKE AS ZACHARIE</hi> after that he had prophecied &amp; ſet forthe Chriſtes incarnation, the moſte comfortable helth &amp; ſaluation of mans ſoule, and lauded &amp; prayſed god therfore, he dyd alſo prophecienge ſet forthe the graciouſe quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of his yonge ſonne Iohn (for as moche as he <note place="margin">Et tu puer ꝓ pheta altiſs<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> mi uocabe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, Prçibis en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ante faciem domini pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare uias eius.</note> then knewe hym by the remembraunce of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelation of the angell before he was conceyued) to be a neceſſary miniſter appoynted of god. and therfore called hym the prophete of the mooſte hygheſt god, to go before hym to make redy his ways, and to do other diuine miniſteries for him. It is conuenient alſo, that we (nowe that Chriſte is playnely and truely by his holy worde ſhewed and ſet forth vnto vs, and as he were newe borne agayne for vs) with all hartye good wyll and mynd ſhuld auance into perpetual fame our ſaid moſte ſoueraygne lorde the kynges moſte excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent maieſtie, whom (by very expert perception of moſt godly commodities) we know nowe to be a neceſſary miniſter of god for our both bodely and goſtly helthe. And as it was ſhewed by the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell, that many ſhulde reioyſe in Iohns natiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
<pb facs="tcp:183786:17"/>
euen ſo haue we great ioye (through the light of goddes holy worde) in the mooſte ryghtuouſe reſtitution of his godlye title power and myny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery ouer vs, wherof he and his moſt noble pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genitours haue be long by vſurpation depriued. And beinge alſo replete with the grace of god, both after the interpretatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the name of Iohn, and his graciouſe antecellent vertues, reſembled to Iohns, and for his bleſſed trauayle in true ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge forthe his lorde and maiſter Chriſte, maye be and ought to be eſtemed of vs an other Iohn Baptiſt, and holy prophete of the mooſte hygheſt god. In whoſe ſyght by his godly minyſtration, his highnes gothe before hym to make redy and playne his wayes in the ſoules of vs his regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate people of Iſraell, commytted by hym to his charge, whoſe hyghnes alſo (declarynge the true <note place="margin">Ad dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſalutis plebi eius.</note> difference betwene the very ryght and pryncypall thynges perteynynge to our ſaluation, and thac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidentall laudable ceremonies and rites, not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teynynge neceſſarylye to our ſaluation: lyke as Iohn Baptiſt putteth difference betwene his ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſme of penaunce in water onely, and Chriſtes baptiſme in the holy goſte, affyrmynge his bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme to gyue neyther remiſſion of ſynne nor ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual grace, but Chriſtes baptiſme to gyue them bothe abundantely) dothe gyue vnto vs (by the ſyncere preachynge and ſettyng forth of the moſt comfortable goſpelle) knowlege and vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge <note place="margin">In remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>catorum eorum.</note> of the helthe of our ſaluation, whiche is Chriſt, the only remytter and pardoner of ſinne,
<pb facs="tcp:183786:17"/>
throughe the tendernes of goddes holy mercy to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes <note place="margin">Per uiſcera miſericordie dei noſtri, in quibus uiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tauit nos o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riens ex alto Zacha. 6. Pſal. 77. Illuminare his qui in te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nebris &amp; in umbra mor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tis ſedent ad dirigendos pedes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtros in uiam pacis.</note> vs. And not by any other meanes or ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, then by the deathe of Chriſt, which for the nones came from aboue, lyke a ſpryngynge light of iuſtice, to lyght vs whiche ſatte and abode lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g both in the darknes of the ignorance of god, &amp; in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhadowe of deth, which folowid vs euery where for our ſynne. And to directe and leade the fete of our ſoules from the obſtinate rebelliouſe genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our forefathers (whoſe hartes were not directe vnto god, nor theyr ſpiryte beleuynge in god, but rather in mennes traditions and ficti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, beſydes Chriſtes goſpell) into the waye of goſtly workes of ryghtuouſnes before god, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is peace with god, to whom be eternall glory prayſe and empire for his before reherſed inenar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable graces and benefytes infuſed in our ſayde moſte ſoueraygne lorde, wherof he hath alſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted vnto vs ſo plentyfully that thrughe the bryght lyght of goddes moſte holy worde, we be bothe borne agayne a peculiar fortunate and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed people of god, in pure knowlege of hym, and alſo delyuered from the horrible &amp; captyue thral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of our moſte cruell and tyrannous enmies the dyuell and the byſhoppe of Rome. Deſyryng yet alſo goddes infinite goodnes, ſo to illumyne (with his holy word) other temporal prynces and rulers, and theyr people (whiche yet ſytte in lyke darkenes and ſhadowe of deathe as we dyd, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe god hath not ſhewed nor opened his iuge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes <note place="margin">Pſal. 147.</note> vnto them, lykewyſe as he hath done vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:183786:18"/>
vs) that they with vs and we with theym (all vſurped power the only rote of diſcorde, betwene and in all nations and of all other abhominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons growen therby clerely extincte) myght parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipate the aforeſayde godly ryghtuouſenes and peace with god. As one heuenly flocke vnder one moſte chiefe herdeman (Chryſte) commytted by hym to the ſondrye charge and gouernaunce of kynges prynces and other temporall rulars vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon erthe: And fynally (hauynge a continual de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoute meditation of goddes ſayd graces and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefytes) Let vs diligently in mooſte harty wyſe (according to Pauls exhortation in this behalfe) praye vnto god, for the moſte ioyfull proſperytie <note place="margin">Tim. 2.</note> and longe good helthe of our ſayde mooſte ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raygne lorde the kynge: the moſte gracious lady quene Anne, his moſte lawfull noble wyfe, and the moſte noble Prynce Edwarde his moſte lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſonne and heyre apparant, and vnto vs moſt excellent preciouſe tewel &amp; treaſure: And that god wyll vouchſafe bothe to adde vnto eyther of the termes of theyr lyues prefinite and appointed, as he added vnto the good Ezechias, and alſo grant that the ſayde Prince may late longe ſuccede his <note place="margin">Ezec. 38.</note> ſayde moſte noble father, bothe in kyngdomeand graciouſe vertues, with increace of chyldren to them bothe alſo, <hi>Vſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> in conſummationem ſeculi,</hi> And after this worldely reygne, celeſtially to reygne with god. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:183786:18"/>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDINI in aedibus Thomae Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleti typis impreſſ. Cum priuilegio ad imprimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum ſolum.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
